So I got the craziest e-mail this morning.
Ce matin, j'ai reçu un e-mail incroyable.
I don't mean to burst your bubble, but penile-enlargement pills do not work.
Au risque de te décevoir,
Believe me, I know.
J'en sais quelque chose.
The e-mail I got was from the office of Stephen Hawking.
L'e-mail Vient du bureau de Stephen Hawking.
-You're kidding. -Why?
- Tu plaisantes ? - Pourquoi ?
He's coming to the university to lecture...
Il va donner une conférence àla fac,
...and he's looking for an engineer to maintain equipment on his wheelchair.
et il cherche un ingénieur pour l‘équipement de son fauteuil.
That's amazing. You'll be like his pit crew.
C‘est incroyable. Tu seras son stand de ravitaillement.
A word of caution, I would not do your Stephen Hawking impression...
Un conseil, évite d'imiter Stephen Hawking
...in front of him.
devant lui.
[MIMICS STEPHEN HAWKING] You're right.
Tu as raison.
[MIMICS STEPHEN HAWKING] I suppose that could be considered offensive.
J‘imagine que ça pourrait être considéré comme insultant.
Oh, boy. Oh, Sheldon's going to freak out.
Sheldon va faire une crise.
Yeah, he worships Hawking.
Oui, il vénère Hawking.
l was thinking about bringing him along, so he can meet the great man.
Je pensais l'amener pour rencontrer le génie.
-That's really nice of you, Howard. -lt's no big deal.
- C‘est gentil de ta part, Howard. - Ce n‘est rien.
Boy, a restraining order from Stephen Hawking.
Une ordonnance restrictive émanant de Stephen Hawking.
It'll look so nice next to the ones he's got...
Il irait si bien avec ceux qu'il a déjà
...from Leonard Nimoy, Carl Sagan and Stan Lee.
de Leonard Nimoy, Carl Sagan et Stan Lee.
Leonard, do you recall when I said that l was going...
Leonard, tu te souviens quand j'ai dit que j'allais
...to revolutionize understanding of the Higgs boson particle...
révolutionner la compréhension du boson de Higgs,
...and you said, "Sheldon, it's 2 am. Get out of my bedroom"?
et tu as dit : “Sheldon, il est 2 h du matin. Sors de ma chambre" ?
Like it was 10 hours ago. What about it?
C'était il y a dix heures. Et alors ?
Well, I believe I've done it.
Je crois que je l'ai fait.
I'm only saying "believe" to sound modest...
Je dis “je crois" pour paraître modeste,
...because, sweet Sam Houston, I did it.
parce que, cher Sam Houston, je l'ai fait.
-Really? -That's incredible. Oh, here.
- Vraiment ? - C‘est incroyable. Tiens.
-Break out the math. -Oh, okay. Let me see this.
- Montre-nous tes calculs. - Bonne—moi ça.
All right, so this particle here is the boson moving forward in time.
Cette particule, c‘est le boson qui avance dans le temps.
Now, I was thinking--
Alors, je pensais...
Howard, you go ahead and eat. This isn't gonna make any sense to you.
Howard, tu peux déjeuner, tu ne vas rien comprendre.
Sheldon, I have a working understanding of physics.
Sheldon, j'ai de bonnes bases en physique.
Yeah, good for you. And don't stop working on it.
C‘est bien. Garde-les.
You still going to tell him...
Tu veux toujours lui dire
-...about you-know-who? -Yep.
a propos de tu-sais-qui ?
-Still gonna introduce him? -Not on your life.
- Tu vas le présenter ? - Jamais dela vie.
Please, please, please. Let me meet Hawking.
Je t'en prie, laisse—moi rencontrer Hawking.
-I told you, no. -But I said I'm sorry.
- Je t'ai dit non. - Mais je me suis excusé.
No, you said, "Would it help ifl said 'l'm sorry'?"
Non, tu as dit: "Accepterais-tu si je m'excuse ?"
Well, and you never answered me.
Tu ne m'as pas répondu.
So who owes whom an apology now?
Qui doit des excuses à qui maintenant ?
Sheldon, you're a condescending jerk.
Sheldon, tu es un goujat condescendant.
Why on earth would I want to do something nice for you?
Pourquoi voudrais-je faire quelque chose de sympa pour toi ?
To go to Jewish heaven?
Pour allez au paradis des juifs ?
Jews don't have heaven.
Les juifs n‘ont pas de paradis.
Well, then, to avoid Jewish hell?
Pour éviter l‘enfer des juifs ?
Have you met my mother? I live in Jewish hell.
Tu connais ma mère ? Je vis dans l'enferjuif.
Howard, please. This is Stephen Hawking.
Howard, je t'en prie. C‘est Stephen Hawking.
Perhaps my only intellectual equal.
Peut-étre mon seul égal intellectuel.
You can't be serious.
Tu n'es pas sérieux ?
Try to put yourself in my place.
Mets—toi a ma place.
Imagine you're the sole human being...
Imagine—toi être le seul être humain
...living on a planet populated with nothing but dogs.
sur une planète peuplée de chiens,
And then it turns out there's another human being.
et il se trouve qu'il y a un autre être humain.
Hang on. Are you saying the rest of us are dogs?
Attends. Tu dis que nous autres sommes des chiens ?
I can see you're gonna take this the wrong way.
Je vois comment tu pourrais mal le prendre.
Let me try again.
Je reprends.
Imagine you're the sole human being...
Imagine être le seul être humain
...living on a planet populated with nothing but chimps.
sur une planète peuplée de chimpanzés.
Get out of my lab.
Sors de mon labo.
Oh, now, they're so much smarter than dogs.
Ils sont tellement plus intelligents que les chiens.
Have you seen them on those little bicycles?
Tu les as déjà vus sur leurs petits Vélos ?
Get out!
Sors d'ici.
-How about dolphins? -Out!
- Et les dauphins ? - Dehors !
So come on, how was the first day with Hawking?
Comment était ce premierjour avec Hawking ?
It was great. We talked about movies.
C‘était super. On a parlé de cinéma.
-I showed him some card tricks. -Oh.
Je lui ai montré des tours de cartes.
He even let me read a couple pages from his new book.
Il m‘a même laissé lire quelques pages de son nouveau livre.
Something got you down there, bunky?
Tu t'es fait piquer par quelque chose ?
Howard, please, I'm begging you.
Howard, je t'en supplie.
Raj, you're our group historian. Has Sheldon ever begged before?
Raj, tu es notre historien. Sheldon a-t-il déjà supplié ?
Three times.
Trois fois.
He begged the Fox network not to cancel Fireﬂy.
Il a supplié la chaîne Fox de ne pas arrêter Fireﬂy.
He begged the TNT network to cancel Babylon 5.
Il a supplié la chaine TNT d‘arrêter Babylon 5.
And when he got food poisoning at the Rose Bowl parade...
Et lors d‘une intoxication alimentaire, le jour de l‘an,
...he begged a deity he doesn't believe in to end his life quickly.
il a supplié une déité a laquelle il ne croit pas, de l'achever.
Do you understand how important Hawking is to me?
Comprends-tu l'importance de Hawking pour moi ?
When I was 6 years old, I dressed up as him for Halloween.
A six ans, je me suis déguisé en lui pour Halloween.
-You're kidding. -No, sir.
- Tu plaisantes. - Pas du tout.
No, I took my dad's desk chair, attached a Speak & Spell to it...
J'ai attaché une dictée magique àla chaise de bureau de mon père,
...and made my sister push me up and down the block to trick-or-treat.
et ma sœur me poussait pour aller collecter des bonbons.
Granted, most people thought I was R2-D2, but still, I got a lot of candy.
Les gens me prenaient pour R2-DZ,
You don't seem to be understanding the English word "no."
On dirait que tu ne comprends pas le mot "non".
Maybe a different language will help.
Essayons dans d'autres langues.
Russian: Nyet. Chinese: bl‘l. Japanese: iie. Klingon: qo'.
Russe : niet.
Binary coded ASCII: 0110111001101111.
Langage binaire codé ASCII : 0110111001101111.
-lt's actually 011011110-- -No!
En fait, c‘est 0110111111...
I'm not asking for me.
Ce n‘est pas pour moi.
I'm asking for Hawking.
C‘est pour Hawking.
Let me try gangster: Hells no.
Version gangster : Ya pas moyen.
Okay, look. How about this?
Bon, j'ai une idée.
You just give him my paper on the Higgs boson.
Donne—lui juste mon article sur le boson de Higgs.
If he sees the breakthrough I've made, he'll reach out to me.
S'il voit ma découverte, il me contactera.
-What if he doesn't? -Yeah, he will. He's really smart.
Et sinon ?
That's an interesting idea.
C‘est une idée intéressante.
Why don't you give me a minute to talk it over with my friends?
Laisse—moi en discuter avec mes amis.
-How? -Walk away.
- Comment ? - Va-t'en.
Walking away!
Je m'en vais.
You do realize you own his ass right now.
Tu te rends compte qu'il est a ta merci.
I do.
Oui.
You can make him do anything you want.
Tu peux lui faire faire tout ce que te veux.
Yeah, I know. I'm just trying to figure out how much I wanna punish him.
Oui, je sais. Je me demande a quel pointje veux le punir.
Well, don't be too mean.
Ne sois pas trop méchant.
...freshly brewed iced tea if anyone would like some.
du thé glacé, si quelqu'un en veut.
-I wouldn't mind a glass. -I wasn't talking to you.
-J'en prendrais bien. - Ce n‘est pas a toi que je parle.
Bring him to his bony knees.
Mets-Ie a genou.
Sheldon, come on back.
Sheldon, reviens.
What did you decide?
Qu'as-tu décidé ?
I'll give your paper to Hawking.
Je vais donner ton article a Hawking.
Great. Thank you. Oh, that's terrific.
Super. Merci. C‘est génial.
But in exchange, I'd like you to do a few things for me.
Mais en échange,
What kinds of things?
Comme ?
Are you familiar with the 12 labors of Hercules?
Tu connais les douze travaux d'Hercule ?
Of course.
Bien sûr.
You should be so lucky.
Dans tes rêves.
All right. What would you like me to do first?
Quelle est ma première tâche ?
Well, I thought I'd start you off by polishing my belt buckles.
Tu peux commencer par le polissage de mes boucles de ceinture.
By all means. Yeah, when l was a boy, I would polish my Mee-Maw's silver.
Bien sûr. Quand j‘étais petit, je polissais l'argenterie de ma mémé.
And she would entertain me with stories about growing up in Oklahoma.
Et elle me racontait des histoires sur sajeunesse dans l‘Oklahoma.
Interesting woman.
Une femme intéressante.
You know, she once killed a prairie dog with a gravy boat.
Un jour, elle atué un chien de prairie avec une sauciére.
That's nice.
Sym pa.
That's a lot of belt buckles.
Ça fait beaucoup de boucles.
Funny thing is I only have one belt.
C‘est drôle, je n'ai qu‘une seule ceinture.
Anyway, I'll let you get started.
Je vais te laisser travailler.
Oh, by the way, the little marks that look like water spots...
Au fait, les petites marques qui ressemblent à des traces d'eau,
...I tend to stand too close to the urinal, so....
j'ai tendance a me tenir trop près de l'urinoir, alors...
What you're seeing there is splash-back.
Ce sont des éclaboussures.
You make sissy on your belt buckles?
Tu fais pipi sur tes boucles de ceinture ?
Mee-Maw's forks never had that.
Les fourchettes de mémé n‘avaient pas ça.
Here is a black light to check them. For your own peace of mind...
Une lumière noire pour les contrôler. Pour ta tranquillité d‘esprit,
...you might not wanna shine that around the rest of the room.
ne l‘utilise pas pour le reste dela chambre.
Sheldon, these look great.
Sheldon, elles sont splendides.
I mean, they're like magnificent little crowns...
On dirait de magnifiques petites couronnes
...to hang over my magnificent little jewels.
à accrocher sur mes magnifiques bijoux.
How did you get them so shiny?
Comment les as-tu fait briller autant ?
Oh, I buffed them with Turtle Wax.
J'ai mis du polish.
The man down at Pep Boys says from now on...
Le type du garage dit que dorénavant,
...the urine should just bead up and roll right off.
l‘urine devrait perler et s'écouler.
Way to go the extra mile. Your Mee-Maw would be proud.
Tu t'es vraiment donné du mal. Ta mémé serait fière.
My Mee-Maw must never know of this.
Ma mémé ne doitjamais savoir.
Now will you give Professor Hawking my paper?
Alors tu vas lui passer mon article ?
Next, this is a sexy French maid costume I bought for Bernadette.
Maintenant, voici un costume de bonne sexy
I thought it might spice things up...
Je croyais que ça pimenterait les choses,
...and get her to dust my room at the same time, heh...
et qu'elle allait aussi dépoussiérer ma chambre.
...but I was wrong and really wrong.
Mais j‘avais tort et vraiment tort.
You want me to return it for you?
Tu veux que j‘aille le rapporter ?
What are you all staring at?
Qu‘est—ce que vous regardez ?
You ever seen a man try to get a meeting with Stephen Hawking before?
Vous n'avez jamais vu un homme
It's not Saturday night. Why are you doing your laundry?
Ce n‘est pas samedi soir. Pourquoi tu fais ta lessive ?
This is not my laundry.
Ce n‘est pas ma lessive.
Wow, are these Amy's? Kind of trashy. Good for her.
C‘est à Amy ? Un peu trash. Tant mieux pour elle.
-Those are Howard's. -Eww.
Ça appartient a Howard.
Why are you washing Howard's man-panties?
Pourquoi laves-tu les culottes d'Howard ?
Because if I don't, he won't give my paper to Stephen Hawking.
Si je ne le fais pas,
-He's a famous physicist-- -Yeah.
C‘est le physicien...
I know. He's the wheelchair dude who invented time.
Je sais. C‘est le type en fauteuil qui a inventé le temps.
Close enough.
Ça fera l'affaire.
Why doesn't Howard just introduce you to the guy?
Pourquoi Howard ne te présentes pas tout simplement ?
Because he's punishing me for being a, quote, "condescending jerk."
Parce qu'il me punit d‘avoir été un, je cite : “goujat condescendant".
You don't think I'm condescending, do you?
Tu ne crois pas que je suis condescendant, si ?
-Well.... -Oh, I'm sorry.
- Eh bien... - Pardon.
-Condescending means-- -I know what it means!
- Condescendant signi... - Je sais !
And, yes, you love correcting people and putting them down.
Oui, tu adores corriger les gens pour les rabaisser.
Au contraire, when I correct people, lam raising them up.
Au contraire, quand je corrige les gens, je les élève.
You should know. I do it for you more than anyone.
Je le fais plus pour toi que quiconque.
Come on, you do it to feel superior.
Tu le fais pour te sentir supérieur.
I see that twinkle when someone says "who" instead of "whom"...
Tes yeux scintillent quand quelqu'un dit ”malgré que",
...or thinks the moon is a planet.
ou pense que la lune est une planète.
Or Don Quixote is a book about a donkey named Hotay.
Ou que Don Quichotte a un don qui est une chiotte.
See? There it is. There's that twinkle.
Regarde. Le voilà, le scintillement.
Well, I can't help it. That's an involuntary twinkle.
Je n‘y peux rien. C‘est un scintillement involontaire.
What do you want me to tell you, Sheldon?
Que veux-tu que je te dise, Sheldon ?
I want you to tell me that Howard is being mean to me for no reason.
Dis—moi qu'Howard est méchant avec moi sans raison.
Fine. Howard is being mean to you for no reason.
Bien. Howard est méchant avec toi sans raison.
I knew it.
Je le savais.
-What's the matter? -Every time I spend the night...
- Ça ne va pas ? - Chaque fois que je dors ici,
...your mom slaps me on the behind and says, "Go get them."
ta mère me tape les fesses et me dit : "Tu les auras."
It's not her fault. She's getting hormone-replacement therapy.
Ce n‘est pas de sa faute. Elle est sous traitement hormonal.
Makes her crazy horny.
Ça l'excite a mort.
Check this out. I got Sheldon to wear the French maid's costume.
Regarde. J'ai forcé Sheldon a porter le costume de bonne.
My God, that's terrible.
Mon Dieu, c‘est horrible.
What? Hey, I gave you first crack at it.
Quoi ? Tu as eu ta chance.
Why are you doing that? You're being mean to him.
Pourquoi tu fais ça ? Tu es méchant avec lui.
He's mean all the time.
Il est méchant avec moi.
You've heard him tease me about not having a doctorate.
Tu l'as entendu me charrier parce que je n'ai pas de doctorat.
You don't wanna get teased about that, get a doctorate.
Si tu ne veux pas être charrié, trouve un doctorat.
l have one. They're great.
J'en ai un. Il est super.
Come on. The man torments me.
Il me torture.
I'm letting him have a little taste of his own medicine.
Je lui rends la monnaie de sa pièce.
It's not the same. Sheldon doesn't know he's being mean. The part of his brain...
Ce n‘est pas pareil.
...that should know is getting a wedgie from the rest of his brain.
qui le devrait se fait bizuter par l‘autre partie.
Fine. I'll just make him do a couple more things, then I'll stop.
Bon. Encore deux ou trois corvées et j'arrêterai.
No, you have to stop now.
Non, arrête dés maintenant.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Bernadette!
Bernadette !
I wanna remind you, you promised to take me dress-shopping tomorrow!
Je te rappelle que tu m'as promis
Oh, damn.
Zut.
I'm sorry, I can't make it!
Je suis désolée, je ne peux pas.
But Sheldon's gonna go with you!
Mais Sheldon ira avec vous.
And that's the last thing you do to him.
Et c‘est la dernière chose que tu lui fais.
I need your help.
J'ai besoin de ton aide.
What is it now, Mrs. Wolowitz?
Quoi encore, Mme Wolowitz ?
MRS. WOLOWITZ: It's this dress.
C‘est la robe.
When I put my front in, my back pops out.
Quand je fais rentrer le devant, mon derrière ressort.
When I put my back in, my front pops out.
Quand je fais rentrer mon derrière, mon devant ressort.
It's like trying to keep two dogs in a bathtub.
C‘est comme essayer de mettre deux chiens dans une baignoire.
What do you want me to do?
Que voulez-vous que je fasse ?
MRS. WOLOWITZ: We're gonna have to work as a team.
Il va falloir travailler en équipe.
Get in here, grab a handful, and start stuffing.
Viens, attrape une poignée, et fourre-Ia dans la robe.
SHELDON: I'm not sure how to do this.
Je ne sais pas comment faire.
MRS. WOLOWITZ: It's easy. Just pretend you're putting away a sleeping bag.
C‘est facile. Imagine que tu plies un sac de couchage.
SHELDON: Sleeping bags don't usually sweat this much, but okay.
Les sacs de couchage ne transpirent pas autant,
MRS. WOLOWITZ: Now zip me up.
Remonte la fermeture éclair.
SHELDON: Oh, if we squeeze you any tighter, you might turn into a diamond.
Si je vous serre encore plus,
MRS. WOLOWITZ: You're right.
Tu as raison.
Who am I kidding?
De qui je me moque ?
You should've seen me when l was young, Sheldon.
Tu aurais dû me voir quand j‘étais jeune, Sheldon.
The fellas used to line up and bring me boxes of candy.
Les garçons faisaient la queue
Why did I eat it all?
Pourquoi les ai-je tous mangés ?
Would you hold me?
Veux-tu me prendre dans tes bras ?
Oh, guys, ljust remembered.
Au fait,
I got you some Hawking souvenirs.
je vous ai rapporté des souvenirs d'Hawking.
What are these?
C‘est quoi ?
Gears and springs from his wheelchair.
Des pièces de son fauteuil.
Pretty cool, huh?
Cool, non ?
Wow. That's amazing.
C‘est incroyable.
Yeah, I made an adjustment on the motor drive...
J'ai fait un réglage sur le moteur,
...and when lwas putting it back together...
et quand je l'ai réassemblé,
...I could not for the life of me figure out where they went.
je n‘avais aucune idée d'où elles venaient.
Idid it.
C‘est fait.
Had to go to three clothing stores...
Nous avons dû faire trois magasins,
...but we finally found a dress that could envelop your mother.
mais nous avons enfin trouvé une robe
I should have sent you to the custom car cover place in Altadena.
J'aurais dû t‘envoyer au magasin de housses de voiture.
They have her pattern on file.
Ils ont ses mensurations.
Ha-ha. Humorous.
Amusant.
Now, will you please present my paper to Professor Hawking?
Pourrais—tu, s'il te plaît, donner mon article au professeur Hawking ?
-I don't know. -Oh, for heaven's sake.
- Je ne sais pas. - Pour l‘amour de Dieu.
I did your laundry. l pee-pee-proofed your belt buckles.
J'ai fait ta lessive. Je t'ai fait des boucles anti—pipi.
I even sprained my wrist helping your mother lift her bosom.
Je me suis même tordu le poignet
All right, Sheldon. There's only one thing left I want you to do.
Trés bien. J'aimerais que tu fasses encore une chose.
-Don't worry, it's an easy one. -Okay.
Ne t'inquiète pas, c‘est facile.
Give me a compliment.
Fais—moi un compliment.
Fine.
D‘accord.
You have very tiny hands.
Tu as des mains minuscules.
No. About myjob.
Non, sur mon travail.
I want you to tell me I'm good at what I do.
Je veux que tu me dises que je suis bon dans ce que je fais.
You're obviously good at what you do.
Tu es évidemment bon dans ce que tu fais.
Well, then, why are you always ripping on me?
Alors pourquoi tu me critiques toujours ?
Oh, I understand the confusion.
Je vois où est le malentendu.
No. l have never said that you are not good at what you do.
Je n'ai jamais dit que tu n‘étais pas bon dans ce que tu faisais.
It's just that what you do is not worth doing.
C'estjuste que ce que tu fais n‘a pas de valeur.
It's nicer than anything he's ever said to me. I'd take it and run.
Il ne m‘ajamais rien dit d‘aussi gentil. Je m'en contenterais.
Thank you, Sheldon.
Merci, Sheldon.
Will you give my paper to Hawking?
Tu donneras mon article a Hawking ?
-Sorry, I can't. -What? Why not?
- Désolé, je ne peux pas. - Pourquoi ?
I gave it to him three days ago.
Je lui ai donné il y a trois jours.
He was really impressed.
Il était très impressionné.
He wants to meet you.
Il veut te rencontrer.
All right, then.
Trés bien.
Thank you, Howard.
Merci, Howard.
Please let Professor Hawking know...
Veux-tu dire au professeur Hawking
...that I'm available at his earliest convenience.
que je suis disponible pour un entretien à sa convenance.
Professor Hawking, it's an honor and a privilege to meet you, sir.
Professeur Hawking, c‘est un honneur de vous rencontrer.
STEPHEN HAWKING [OVER COMPUTER]: Iknow.
Je sais.
I wanna thank you for taking time to see me.
Je voudrais vous remercier de prendre le temps de me recevoir.
My pleasure.
Je vous en prie.
I enjoyed reading your paper very much.
J‘ai apprécié votre article.
You clearly have a brilliant mind.
Vous avez un esprit brillant.
I know.
Je sais.
Your thesis that the Higgs boson is a black hole...
Votre thèse selon laquelle le boson de Higgs est un trou noir
...accelerating backwards through time is fascinating.
accélérant dans le sens inverse du temps est fascinante.
Thank you. ltjust-- It came to me one morning in the shower.
Merci. Ca m‘est venu un matin sous la douche.
That's nice.
C ‘est bien.
Too bad it's wrong.
Dommage qu‘elle soit fausse.
What do you mean, "wrong"?
Que voulez-vous dire ?
You made an arithmetic mistake on page two.
Vous avez fait une erreur d‘arithmétique, page 2.
It was quite the boner.
C‘était une sacrée gaﬁe.
No, no. But that can't be right.
Non, c‘est impossible.
I don't make arithmetic mistakes.
Je ne fais jamais d'erreur d‘arithmétique.
Are you saying I do?
Suggérez-vous que j‘en fais ?
Oh, no. No, no, of course not.
Non, bien sûr que non.
It's just, I was thinking-- Oh, gosh, golly. I made a boo-boo.
Je pensais juste...
And I gave it to Stephen Hawking.
Etje l'ai donnée a Stephen Hawking.
Great. Another fainter.
Super. Encore un autre qui s ‘évanouit.
[English - us - an]
[French]